Finding Aid for Arthur F. Southwick papers, 1958-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur F. Southwick papers 1958-1996
Southwick, Arthur F.
2 linear feet
03112 Aa 2
Arthur F. Southwick was a distinguished professor in the School of Business Administration and the School of Public Health at the University of Michigan. His dedication to teaching and research put him at the forefront of his specialization in health care business law and medical ethics. His papers are filled with his research in the areas of physician liability, medical information privacy, consent issues, civil rights, automation of medical records, reproductive freedom, and medical staff privileges.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The library received the papers in January 2003 (Donor no. 9311 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur Southwick received a Bachelor of Arts degree from Wooster College in 1947. His graduate studies led him to the University of Michigan where he received a Masters in Business Administration in 1950 and a Juris Doctor degree in 1951. Southwick became a University of Michigan faculty member in 1956 as an assistant professor of Business Law in the School of Business Administration. He advanced to associate professor in 1961 and to full professor in 1966. In 1975, he also became a professor of Hospital Administration, now known as Health Services Management and Policy within the School of Public Health.
Throughout his career, Southwick was known for his outstanding service to his students and his field of research. At his retirement, the Board of Regents reflected on his years of devotion to his students. They noted how Professor Southwick's courses contained "lively classroom coverage of complex legal issues" and that he often devoted much of his time to students' issues and research ideas. Professor Southwick's love for teaching is shown through his ample files of teaching notes within these papers. Letters of appreciation from former students fill his correspondence file.
Southwick believed that current research was necessary to provide the best possible classroom leadership. His files reveal active interests within many areas of health administration and business law. The papers contain only a few of his many publications, including the widely used and cited The Law of Hospital and Health Care Administration. He also published many book chapters and articles, influencing health care practices, ethics, regulations, and law. Professor Southwick was also on the editorial board of the American Journal of Law and Medicine and served on the editorial advisory board for Issues in Health Care Technology and Hospital Risk Control. He was a member of the American Academy of Health Care Attorneys, the Academy of Legal Studies in Business, the National Health Lawyers Association, and the American Society of Law, Medicine, and Ethics.
Arthur Southwick's achievements have been honored in many ways. The University of Michigan School of Business Administration offers an award in his name. The Southwick Award is annually given to the undergraduate student that submits the best paper in Business Administration course 380: Business Law Senior Seminar, an honors-type class culminating in a major research paper. The award recognizes Arthur Southwick as an outstanding teacher and researcher.
Arthur Southwick retired from the University of Michigan in 1990. He was granted professor emeritus status in health services management and policy from the School of Public Health and in business law from the School of Business Administration upon retirement.
He passed away March 3, 1997 at the age of 73.
The Arthur F. Southwick Papers are divided into four series: Biographical Materials, Publications, Subject Files, and Teaching Notes. The papers retain their original series groupings. Folders are arranged in alphabetical order within each series according to their original folder labels. Full text legal cases were removed from the folders as well as articles from widely available sources such as The New York Times and The Washington Post.
Subjects:
Southwick, Arthur F.; Medical care--Law and legislation--United States.; Hospitals--Law and legislation--United States.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical Materials series (1959-1987, 0.2 linear feet) contains professional correspondence and photographs of Arthur Southwick. Many of the letters express gratitude toward Southwick for presentations, publications, teaching, and his general professional activities. The correspondence reveals the depth and breadth of his work as well as the positive influence he had on the health care administration and legal issues fields throughout his career. The photographs folder contains images of Southwick speaking at a presentation in 1971.
  - Photographs, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Professional Recognition Correspondence 1959-1987 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts and Publication Records 1967-1994
  The Manuscripts and Publication Records series (1967-1994, 0.3 linear feet) contains a sample of Arthur Southwick's writings and accompanying documentation. The majority of the Publications Series documents the creation and revisions of Southwick's notable book Law of Hospital and Health Care Administration. It includes drafts, notes, correspondence, reviews, and publicity. About half of the material describes Southwick's original book and additional editions. However, additional folders describe an accompanying manual, Law of Hospital and Health Care Administration: Cases and Materials, compiled by J. Stuart Showalter and Bernard D. Reams, Jr., based on Southwick's original text. These folders contain correspondence between the editors and Southwick as well as Southwick's notes and responses to the manual. The Medical Staff Privileges folder holds many articles, both published and manuscript copies, regarding the rights and responsibilities of physicians and hospitals.
  - Law of Hospital and Health Care Administration
    - Cases and Materials, edited by J. Stuart Showalter and Bernard D. Reams, Jr. with a forward by Arthur F. Southwick
      - Proof and Publicity 1991-1993 (Box 1)
      - Text, Correspondence, Notes, and Reviews 1986-1993 (Box 1)
    - Permission Letters 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Preface, Acknowledgments, Contents Revisions 1978-1991 (Box 1)
    - Second Edition Revisions and Reviews 1984-1988 (Box 1)
    - Self-Directed Learning Component
      - Draft 1991 (Box 1)
      - Outlines and Articles 1985-1994 (Box 1)
  - Medical Staff Privileges 1967-1981 (Box 1)
  - Quality Assurance in Health Care: Confidentiality of Information and Immunity of Participants 1984 (Box 1)
- Subject Files 1959-1996
  Southwick's Subject Files (1959-1996, 0.3 linear feet) are an accumulation of information regarding a number of topics that he studied. Most of the folders contain newsclippings, health and law bulletins, notes about the topic, bibliographies, institutional policies, and references to pertinent legal cases. These files are a more general grouping of information than the folders within the Teaching Notes subseries.
  - AIDS Task Force-Michigan 1987-1991 (Box 1)
  - Artificial Insemination and Surrogate Motherhood 1967-1992 (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights Act of 1991, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Consent-Research, Innovative Therapy Experimentation 1982-1991 (Box 1)
  - Court System-Jurisdiction, Jury Trial 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - Damages, Punitive 1983-1991 (Box 1)
  - Family Law 1991 (Box 1)
  - First Amendment 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Freedom of Information Acts, Privacy Act, Open Meetings 1973-1987 (Box 1)
  - Medical Ethics 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - Medical Records Content, Retention, Ownership 1964-1993 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Malpractice and Hospital Liability 1979-1990 (Box 1)
  - Organization of University Hospitals 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Title VII-Fair Employment
    - Race, Religion, Origin 1986-1991 (Box 1)
    - Sex/Pregnancy 1979-1991 (Box 1)
- Teaching Notes 1958-1995
  Teaching Notes (1958-1995, 1.2 linear feet) comprise the remainder of the papers. Most of the folders are labeled for specific classes taught by Southwick. Topics within the General Subjects subseries were not designated for a particular class. These folders contain handwritten outlines and notes about each subject. They also occasionally hold newspaper clippings, references to legal proceedings, and articles relevant to the subject. Notes for specific courses are organized by department and number under the Classes subseries heading. Course titles changed often within Southwick's teaching career and every attempt has been made to include the most relevant variations. Regardless of school or department, Southwick's notes all hold similar contents including lecture outlines and notes, relevant articles and newsclippings, listings of bibliographical sources, and occasional syllabi, course descriptions, assignments, and reading lists. Most of the notes are not dated. Southwick also collected other course materials for some classes that he previously taught, mainly in the Health Management and Policy Department within the School of Public Health.
  - Classes
    - Law, History, and Communication (School of Business Administration) and Health Management and Policy (School of Public Health)
      - 305/515: Business Law/Legal Environment
        - Exams and Problem Cases 1986-1988 (Box 1)
        - Introduction to Law 1961-1987 (Box 1)
      - 530: Legal Aspects of Regulation of the Health Care
        - Bill Rights-Press, Speech, Religion 1988-1990 (Box 1)
        - Course Pack-Administrative Regulation 1986 (Box 1)
      - LHC 515/HSMP 652 International Business Law
        - Introduction to Contracts Law 1958-1984 (Box 1)
        - Powers Government to Regulate-Fourteenth Amendment (Box 1)
        - Torts (Box 1)
    - Law, History, and Communication (School of Business Administration) and Health Management and Policy (School of Public Health)
      - LHC 515/LHC 530/HSMP 652 Constitutional Law-Structure, Bill Rights, Judicial Review circa 1985-1989 (Box 1)
      - LHC 530/HSMP 659 Legal Aspects of Regulation of the Health Care Industry
        - Affirmative Action 1986-1991 (Box 2)
        - AIDS-Legal Issues 1987-1991 (Box 2)
        - Assignment Sheets-Professor Arthur Southwick 1987-1988 (Box 2)
        - Coursepack-Fair Employment 1986 (Box 2)
        - Exams and Problem Cases 1986-1988 (Box 2)
        - Title VII-Affirmative Action-Source File 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Health Management and Policy (School of Public Health)
      - 652: Law of Hospital and Health Care Administration
        - Abortion (Box 2)
        - Assignment Sheets
          - Professor Peter Jacobson 1996 (Box 2)
          - Professor Judy Ogden 1990-1995 (Box 2)
          - Professor Arthur Southwick 1989-1990 (Box 2)
        - Common Law and Equity-Source of Law 1958-1989 (Box 2)
        - Living Will and Durable Power of Attorney (Box 2)
        - Medical Records
          - Duty to Maintain and Out-of-Court Disclosure circa 1950s-1990 (Box 2)
          - Duty to Report-Child Abuse (Box 2)
          - Duty to Warn-Tarasoff (Box 2)
          - Privilege-Court Disclosure (Box 2)
        - Pre-Natal Torts (Box 2)
        - Sterilization (Box 2)
      - 659: Legal Aspects of Regulation of the Health Care Industry
        - Assignment Sheets-Professor Judy Ogden 1991-1993 (Box 2)
        - Certificate of Need and Planning 1977-1987 (Box 2)
        - Fair Employment-Civil Rights-Title VII (Box 2)
    - Public Health Policy and Administration (School of Public Health) 653: The Role of Law in Public Health Policy, Professor Toby Citrin 1988 (Box 2)
  - General Subjects
    - Advertising-Commercial Speech (Box 2)
    - Anti Trust, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Court System-Jurisdiction-Jury Trial (Box 2)
    - Criminal Law (Box 2)
    - Products Liability-Warranties, Negligent Design (Box 2)
    - Strict Tort Liability-Duty to Warn (Box 2)
    - Tort-Inter-Family/Spousal Immunity (Box 2)
    - Tort Reform (Box 2)